Preliminary Guide to the Bradbury Thompson Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Bradbury Thompson papers
1945-2002
1945-1993
MS 1794
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
127.5
The papers consist of correspondence, design work products, publications, and visual materials documenting the professional career of Bradbury Thompson.
Thompson, Bradbury
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Deen Dodge Thompson, 2003 and 2005.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Arrangement
Arranged in thirteen series and one addition.
Biographical / Historical
James Bradbury Thompson, prominent graphic designer, was born in Topeka, Kansas, on March 25, 1911. He began designing books in high school, where he designed yearbooks, and designed his college yearbook at Washburn College, where he obtained a B.A. in economics in 1934. Thereafter he worked in New York City as a designer, and served as art director for the Office of War Information's publications division from 1942-1945. Thompson was well-known for his long association with the West Virginia Pulp and Paper Company (Westvaco), for which he designed the American Classic Book Series. He was art director of Mademoiselle for fourteen years, and throughout his career, he designed or redesigned more than thirty five magazines, including Business Week and the Smithsonian Magazine. In 1969, Thompson was commissioned by Marshall Field IV to design a Bible similar to the Gutenberg folio edition. Four hundred copies of The Washburn College Bible were published in 1979 by Oxford University Press, and it became an instant classic. Thompson received many awards and honors during his lifetime, including gold medals from the American Institute of Graphic Arts, and the National Society of Art Directors. For many years he was a visiting critic and visiting professor at the Yale University School of Art and Architecture. He married Della Deen Dodge in 1934 and they had four children. Bradbury Thompson died on November 1, 1995.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of correspondence, design work products, publications, and visual materials documenting the professional career of Bradbury Thompson.
Commercial art; Graphic arts; Thompson, Bradbury; Washburn College; Westvaco Corporation; Yale University. School of Art and Architecture
- Works by Thompson, Series I
  - Westvaco Chrismas books, 1975-1983 (Box 1)
  - The Art of Graphic Design (Box 2)
  - Famous Artists Magazine; Famous Writers School; Set to Fit, UCLA Extension, 1970-1990 (Box 3)
  - Bell Laboratories; Famous Writers School study guides, Westvaco Christmas books, 1971-1980 (Box 4)
  - Famous Artists Advanced Program (Box 5–6)
  - AIGA; exhibition brochure; First Congregational Church; Pitney Bowes; Greenwish Arts Council; Westvaco Christmas books, 1965-1982 (Box 7)
  - Washburn College Bible; David Wynne exhibition; Westvaco, 1972-1980 (Box 8)
  - Famous Artists courses (Box 9–10)
  - Famous Writers School; Famous Photographers Course/School; Famous Artists Magazine, Famous Artists Course; American Institute of Graphic Arts, 1950s-1970s (Box 11–14)
  - Art News Annual, 1945-1971 (Box 15)
  - Portfolio; AIGA; Westvaco, 1959-1977 (Box 16)
  - Westvaco, 1963-1973 (Box 17)
  - Gibson; AIGA; Cornell; Famous Artists Course; Handbook; Washburn College Bible; Art of Graphic Design (Box 18)
  - Portfolio; Art News Annual, 1946-1972 (Box 19–22)
  - Office of War Information pamphlets; miscellaneous (Box 23–24)
  - Early works, yearbooks, miscellaneous (Box 25)
  - Greeting cards; Pitney Bowes; Lindemeyer (Box 26)
  - Dutch Treat Club; miscellaneous (Box 27)
  - Annual report; corporate; Jones park; misc (Box 28)
  - Menninger; AIGA; colleges (Box 29)
  - Art News; miscellaneous publications (Box 30)
  - Westvaco; NSAD award; correspondence; miscellaneous publications (Box 31)
  - Miscellaneous publications (Box 32)
  - Elizabeth Dodge; Westvaco; miscellaneous publications (Box 33)
  - Sample books Office of War Information; cut copies; annual reports; miscellaneous reports (Box 34)
  - Miscellaneous publications, book plates (Box 35)
  - Original art work for Office of War Information; miscellaneous publications (Box 36)
  - Miscellaneous publications (Box 37–38)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 39–43)
  - Project Correspondence (Box 44)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 45–52)
  - Miscellaneous magazines (Box 53)
  - Clients
    - American Institute of Graphic Arts [AIGA]; American Machinist; American Paper Institute; Art Directors Club (Box 54)
    - Bell Laboratories; CGF Indistries (Box 55)
    - Colleges and universities (Box 56)
    - Container Corporation; Cooper Union [exhibition] (Box 57)
    - Davis Delaney, Inc (Box 58)
    - Dutch Treat Book Club; Ford Today; Fortune; Gibson; G.A. Yearbook [Graphic Arts?]; Greenwich (Box 59)
    - Hallmark; Harvard Business Review (Box 60)
    - Jesn Risom Design; Pimny Exhibit; Pitney Bowes (Box 61)
    - Printers Industries; Progressive Architecture; Rand Associates (Box 62)
    - Readers Digest (Box 63)
    - Saturday Review; Smithsonian (Box 64)
    - Society of Illustrators; Stephen Colhoun (Box 65)
    - Textile World; Time-Life; Troug Nichols (Box 66)
  - Advertising (Box 67)
  - Books general; book jackets
  - Homage to the Book (Box 68–69)
  - Calendars; holidays; fashions (Box 70)
  - Framed designs (Box 71–72)
  - Layouts (Box 73)
  - Magazines; newspapers (Box 74)
  - Mounted designs [chronological run] (Box 75–77)
  - Posters (Box 78–80)
  - Sketches; designs (Box 81–82)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 83)
- Works About Bradbury Thompson/Personal, Series II
  - High Quality; recent publications; Graphic Design in America exhibition catalog; posters; 40thAnnual of Advertising and Editorial Art & Design; Art directing; Exempla Graphica; Illustrators 15; Hurlburt; Novum Gebrauchgraphik; Including Computer Art and Design; Point of Sale, 1952-1993 (Box 84)
  - Miscellaneous publications (Box 85)
  - Baseline; Smithsonian; 48thAnnual of Advertising, Editorial & Television Art & Design; A History of Graphic Design; Graphic Style from Victorian to Post-Modern; Graphic Design in America; Nine Pioneers in American Graphic Design; Typographic Communications Today; Print; Self; 50 Plus; Town & Country (Box 86)
  - Clippings; Washburn Bible press; press general; miscellaneous (Box 87–90)
  - American Typography Today; The Grid; Communication arts; miscellaneous publications (Box 91)
  - Personal, general (Box 92)
  - Norman Ives (Box 93)
  - Personal, general (Box 94–96)
  - Photographs (Box 97)
  - Portfolios (Box 98–100)
- Stamps, Series III
  - Stamp design materials, miscellaneous publications (Box 101–108)
- Yale University, Series IV
  - Course materials for graphic design courses (Box 109)
  - Traveling exhibit materials, Yale library show, correspondence, course materials (Box 110–111)
  - Books by students in Thompson classes (Box 112)
- Westvaco, Series V
  - Design materials, correspondence, layouts, clippings (Box 113–133)
- Bibles (mostly Washburn College Bible), Series VI
  - Layout sheets, reports, miscellaneous (Box 134–136)
  - Correspondence (Box 137–139)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 140–147)
- Correspondence, Series VII
  - General (Box 148)
  - Miscellaneous, 1960s-1980s (Box 149–150)
  - Trip notes and miscellaneous (Box 151)
  - Greenwich, Arts Council, Perrot Library, 350th (Box 152)
  - Professional associations (Box 153)
  - Christmas cards from other artists (Box 154)
  - Menninger; Westvaco (Box 155)
  - Business correspondence and design (Box 156–160)
- Books by Thompson, Series VIII
  Scope and Contents
  The series includes materials relating to two books by Bradbury Thompson: Art of Graphic Design and Design and Typography.
  - Correspondence, chapters, design materials (Box 161–162)
- Privately Published Books, Series IX
  - Privately published books (Box 163–164)
- Collected Materials, Series X
  - Color samples; designs by others [designs sent by others to Thompson] (Box 165)
  - Maps (Box 166)
  - Newspapers (Box 167)
  - Posters--Finn Typographic Services (Box 168)
  - Posters--general (Box 169)
  - Source materials [used for inspiration?] (Box 170–174)
- Mademoiselle Magazine and Victory Magazine, Series XI
  - Mademoiselle
    - 1945-1947 (Box 175)
    - 1947-1948 (Box 176)
    - 1948-1950 (Box 177)
    - 1950-1952 (Box 178)
    - 1952-1953 (Box 179)
    - 1954-1956 (Box 180)
    - 1956-1958 (Box 181)
    - 1958-1959 (Box 182)
  - Victory
    - Volume I (Box 183)
    - Volume II (Box 184)
- Slides, Series XII
  - Westvaco; 100 inspirations; envelopes; anagraphics; Washburn, Yale University class products, 1976-1994 (Box 185–190)
- Samples, Series XIII
  - Samples (Box 191–193)
- Additional Material, Accession 2006-M-046
  - Acknowledgment from the White House for gift of Washburn College Bible, 1982 January 11 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Scott, Douglass. "Bradbury Thompson, Designer and Teacher, 1911-1995," Print L: III(1996), 110-113, 1996 May/June (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Stapp, William F. Portrait of the Art World: A Century of ARTnews Photographs, Washington, D. C. National Portrait Gallery, Smithsonian Institution, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 3)